Guide to the William Shockley and Eugenics Collection
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
William Shockley and eugenics collection
1966-1978
SC0595
Saunders, John Bertrand deCusance Morant, 1903-
2 Linear feet
This collection pertains to Shockley's work on heredity, I.Q., and race and includes papers and articles by Shockley, including several presented to the National Academy of Sciences; two issues of the PHI DELTA KAPPAN containing a debate between Shockley and N. L. Gage (Stanford professor of education) on heredity, environment, race, and I.Q., 1972; and clippings on Shockley's views as well as reactions to them, particularly in the academic world. Some of the clippings concern the controversy at Stanford when Shockley's proposed graduate class on dysgenics (1972) was not approved.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Eleanor Thompson Wortz, 2000; purchase, 2013.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Description of the Collection
The materials consist of correspondence, news clippings, publications and ephemera related to Shockley's work on heredity, I.Q., and race.
Accession ARCH-2000-263 includes papers and articles by Shockley, including several presented to the National Academy of Sciences; two issues of the PHI DELTA KAPPAN containing a debate between Shockley and N. L. Gage (Stanford professor of education) on heredity, environment, race, and I.Q., 1972; and clippings on Shockley's views as well as reactions to them, particularly in the academic world. Some of the clippings concern the controversy at Stanford when Shockley's proposed graduate class on dysgenics (1972) was not approved.
Accession ARCH-2007-074 consists of materials, originally part of William Spicer's files, pertaining to William Shockley's interest in eugenics and heredity. Included are two papers by Shockley, "Possible Transfer of Metallurgical and Astronomical Approaches to the Problem of Environment versus Ethnic Heredity," 1966, and "City Slums and Research Taboos - A National Sickness Diagnosed," 1967; Shockley's letter to Spicer regarding the U.S. News and World Report interview with Shockley, 1965 (copy attached); form letter by Shockley in response to his 1965 talk on "Population Control and Eugenics" with 17 enclosures (articles, press releases, and other correspondence, including George W. Beadle); and form letter by Shockley requesting feedback on his drafted response to criticisms from faculty in the Genetics Department of S. U. School of Medicine, 1966.
Accession ARCH-2013-060 consists of Shockley and Foundation for Research and Education on Eugencis and Dysgenics (FREED) correspondence, news clippings, publications, and ephemera originally part of John B. deC. M. Saunders' files.
Arrangement note
The materials are arranged by accession.
Access Terms
Gage, N. L., (Nathaniel Lees), 1917-2008; Karkau, Isabel Steiner; Shockley, William, 1910-1989.; Wortz, Eleanor Thompson; Academic freedom.; Eugenics.; Heredity, Human.; Human genetics.
Collection Contents
- Eugenics papers, 1966-1976; Karkau, Isabel Steiner; Accession ARCH-2000-263 (Box 1)
  Isabel Steiner Karkau was an engineering student at Stanford University in the 1930s. William Shockley was professor of engineering at Stanford (1958-1975) and co-recipient of the Nobel Prize in physics, 1956.
  - Papers, remarks by Schockley, 1970-1973 (Box 1, 1, Folder 1)
  - Shockley reprints, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Phi Delta Kappan, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - SWOPSI matter, 1972 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Undergraduate Studies review of SWOPSI matter, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Biographical material, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Eugenics papers, 1965-1970; Spicer, William E., collector.; Acccesion ARCH-2007-074 (Box 1)
  William E. Spicer was a professor in the Department of Electrical Engineering at Stanford University, 1962-1992.
  This collection of miscellaneous materials, originally part of William Spicer's files, pertains to William Shockley's interest in eugenics and heredity. The collection includes two papers by Shockley, "Possible Transfer of Metallurgical and Astronomical Approaches to the Problem of Environment versus Ethnic Heredity," 1966, and "City Slums and Research Taboos - A National Sickness Diagnosed," 1967; Shockley's letter to Spicer regarding the U.S. News and World Report interview with Shockley, 1965 (copy attached); form letter by Shockley in response to his 1965 talk on "Population Control and Eugenics" with 17 enclosures (articles, press releases, and other correspondence, including George W. Beadle); and form letter by Shockley requesting feedback on his drafted response to criticisms from faculty in the Genetics Department of S. U. School of Medicine, 1966.
  - Shockley, William, "City slums and research taboos", 1967 Jan 11 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Shockley, William, "Possible transfer of metallurgical and astronomical approaches to the problem of environment versus ethnic heredity", 1966 Oct 15 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Shockley, William, letter to Spicer, 1965 Nov 16 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Shockley, William, form letter and enclosures, 1966 Sep 6 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Shockley, William, form letter re: comments from genetics faculty, 1966 Apr 14 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Shockley, William, correspondence re: lab security, 1970 Jul 15 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Eugenics papers, 1966-1978; Saunders, John Bertrand deCusance Morant, 1903-; Accession ARCH-2013-060
  Son of a British surgeon, J.B.deC.M. Saunders was born in Grahamstown, South Africa in 1903, and educated there. He took his M.B., Ch.B at the University of Edinburgh in 1925, becoming FRCS, Edinburgh in 1930. Dr. Saunders came to UCSF in 1931 as Asst. Professor of Anatomy, becoming Professor and Chair of the Dept. of Anatomy in 1938, a post he held until 1956. He has also served the campus as Dean, School of Medicine (1956-63), Chair, Dept. of Medical History and Bibliography (1937-73), and University Librarian (1943-1973). In 1959 Dr. Saunders was inaugurated as the first Provost of the UCSF campus, was named the first Chancellor of UCSF in 1964, and served in that position until 1966. In that year he was named to the Regents Chair of Medical History, in the Department of the History of Health Sciences.
  Dr. Saunders has carried out research in several areas, including medical history (works on Vesalius and ancient medicine) and the structure and development of bones, the physiology of the muscles and the mechanics of walking. He was a member of numerous professional and honorary societies, among them the Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh, the American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgeons, the American Association of Anatomists, and the American and British Medical Associations.
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Shockley-Seitz (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Publications (Box 3, Folder 16)